Guide to the Baptist Church of Galen, New York records,1830-1865.
Baptist Church of Galen, New York records,1830-1865
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Baptist Church of Galen, New York records, 1830-1865.
6009
Baptist Church of Galen, (Galen, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm, 1 folder.
Microfilm, record book.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
One volume record book (1830-1843) containing the church covenant, a list of members (1831) and covenant, minutes, extracts from church records (1843-1865) prepared by Virginia Moscrip (June 1966), a list of those buried at the Old Village Cemetery in Clyde prepared by Mrs. H.T. Jeffry.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Baptist Church of Galen (Clyde) was formed in 1818-19 when a fev citizens met together, were organized into a regular Baptist Church, adopted articles of faith, subscribed to a covenant, and elected officers. Early members included Rev. Jared Blackman, Rev. Joseph Potter, (the first pastor), Joel Blackman, John Flint and Joel B. Potter. The church incorporated on April 21, 1832. That same year Dr. James Dickson donated land for a church which was constructed the following year on Sodus Street. In 1864 the church reformed after having dissolved itself in l86l or 1864, and called itself the First Baptist Church of Clyde. In 1954 the church united with the Baptist Church of Rose. See: History of Wayne County, N.Y. p. 88 or Item 2, p. 1 for additional information.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
These records contain a one volume record book (1830-1843) containing the church covenant, a list of members (1831) and covenant, regular and special church meeting minutes which include accounts of church discipline, the spiritual state of the congregation, letters of dismission and acceptance of new members; extracts from the church records (1843-1865) prepared by Miss Virginia Moscrip, (June 1966) containing a history of the church, provenance of the records and a membership list; a list of those buried at the Old Village Cemetary in Clyde prepared by Mrs. H.T. Jeffry, and a list of N.Y. state marriages performed by Rev, Alfred E. Roe copied by Mrs. W.W. Reed.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Baptist Church of Galen, (Galen, N.Y.); Blackman, Jared.; Jeffrey, H.T.,; Moscrip, Virginia.; Potter, Joseph.; Old Village Cemetery (Clyde, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Baptists--New York (State)--Galen.; Cemeteries--New York (State)--Clyde.
Places:
Galen (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Record Book, 1830-1843, Item I
  - Sat. June 26, 1830
    Minutes commence.
  - Feb. 26, 1831
    Shakers
  - Apr. 12, 1831
    H
  - Aug. 27, 1831
    Port Bay Church formation The church leaves the Cayuga Baptist Association to join the Ontario Association which is closer, appointment of a committee to look for land for a meeting house.
  - Apr. 21, 1832
    church is incorporated as the Baptist Church in Clyde.
  - Aug. 12, 1832
    an ordination council is called.
  - Aug. 23, 1832
    meeting ordains Bro. Like Morley, delegates listed.
  - Nov. 24, 1832
    a Presbyterian converts.
  - Dec. 12, 1832
    his wife converts.
  - Jan. 23, 1833
    bro, becomes a freewill Baptist.
  - Jan. 29, l834-Feb.3
    a revival occurs.
  - Nov. 26, 1836
    delegates are appointed to attend the Wayne Bible Society.
  - Jan, 21, 1837
    Tyre and Junius minister is ordained, delegates sent.
  - Oct. 24, 1837
    a Methodist joins.
  - Dec. 23, 1837
    a revival is planned.
  - Jan. 20, 1838
    Converts enter.
  - Jan. 27, 1838
    more converts
  - Apr. 7, 1838
    Articles of Faith and Covenant approved.
  - Oct. 31, 1838
    Rufus K. Bellamy is ordained.
  - Aug. 25, 1839
    statistics of the church for the annual letter.
  - Dec. 22, 1839
    a protracted meeting.
  - March 7, 1840
    a Methodist converts.
  - July 11, 1840
    Resolutions on Sabbath collection, treasurer's reports ,and a Ways and Means committee.
  - Aug. 1840
    statistics for the annual letter.
  - Aug. 2, 1842
    statistics for the annual letter, the congregation has begun to call itself the First Baptist Church in Clyde.
  - May 15, 1843
    last minutes, 2 pp, of notes on subscriptions
  - n.d.
    List of members of the Church with name, occasionally age and where born, whether received by baptism or letter, experience, excluded, dismissed, died, and comments.
- Extracts from the Records of the Baptist Church of Clyde, Town of Galen, 1843-1865, Item 2
  Contains a history of the church, provenance of the records, and the membership list. 23 pp.
- List of those buried at the Old Village Cemetary in Clyde. 5 pp., Item 3
- A list of N.Y. State marriages performed by Rev. Alfred E. Roe, Item 4
  Containing name, age, home town, witnesses, whether first marriage, and parents of the couple. 3 pp.